<chapter>
<title>Download and install the latest ReactOS release binaries</title>

<!--
<artheader>
   <title>Downloading and installing the latest ReactOS binaries</title>
   <author>
      <firstname>Jason</firstname>
      <surname>Filby</surname>
      <affiliation>
        <address>
          <email>jasonfilby@yahoo.com</email>
        </address>
      </affiliation>
   </author>
</artheader>
-->

<abstract>
<para>
Where to get the latest ReactOS binaries and how to install them.
</para>
</abstract>

<sect2>
<title>Where to download from</title>
<para>
ReactOS binaries are physically stored on ReactOS' SourceForge development site. You can download ReactOS directly from the SourceForge site, but some users may prefer to go via ReactOS.com.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Obtaining the latest binaries via reactos.com</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Visit <ulink url="http://reactos.com">reactos.com</ulink> which is the ReactOS portal site. This site will always point to the latest binaries.</para></listitem>
<listitem>Click on the link, on the opening page of reactos.com that points to the latest "Kernel Release".</listitem>
<listitem>On the Latest Release page, click on the "Download kernel x.x.xx binaries" (eg. "Download kernel 0.0.18 binaries") link.</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Obtaining the latest binaries via SourceForge</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>Visit <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/reactos">sourceforge.net/projects/reactos</ulink> which is ReactOS' development site, hosted by SourceForge.</listitem>
<listitem>Scroll down to the "Latest File Releases"</listitem>
<listitem>Click on the "Download" link for the reactos package.</listitem>
<listitem>Scroll down to the reactos package (should be hilighted purple) and click on the xxxx_binary.zip (eg. 0018_binary.zip) link to download the binaries.</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Installing the binaries</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>Use your favourite zip utility to open the downloaded binary file.</listitem>
<listitem>Extract the binaries to c:\ (the archive has path information to extract under c:\reactos).</listitem>
<listitem>Check that the binaries are installed under c:\reactos (not c:\reactos\reactos!).</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
<emphasis>Note:</emphasis> You must extract the binaries to c:\reactos (first partition of first hard drive) if you wish to boot ReactOS under real hardware (DOS or boot loader).
</para>
<para>
<emphasis>Note:</emphasis> If you are going to use emulation software (we recommend Bochs; see Bochs documentation) to test ReactOS, then it does not matter where you extract to.
</para>
</sect2>

</chapter>
