<refentry id="generate.toc">
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>generate.toc</refentrytitle>
<refmiscinfo role="type">table</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>
<refnamediv>
<refname>generate.toc</refname>
<refpurpose>Control generation of ToCs and LoTs</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<refsynopsisdiv>
<src:fragment id='generate.toc.frag'>
<xsl:param condition="html" name="generate.toc">
appendix  toc
article   toc
book      toc,figure,table,example,equation
chapter   toc
part      toc
preface   toc
qandadiv  toc
qandaset  toc
reference toc
section   toc
set       toc
</xsl:param>
<xsl:param condition="fo" name="generate.toc">
/appendix toc
/article  toc
book      toc,figure,table,example,equation
/chapter  toc
part      toc
/preface  toc
qandadiv  toc
qandaset  toc
reference toc
/section  toc
set       toc
</xsl:param>
</src:fragment>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsect1><title>Description</title>

<para>This parameter has a structured value. It is a table of space-delimited
path/value pairs. Each path identifies some element in the source document
using a restricted subset of XPath (only the implicit child axis, no wildcards,
no predicates). Paths can be either relative or absolute.</para>

<para>When processing a particular element, the stylesheets consult this table to
determine if a ToC (or LoT(s)) should be generated.</para>

<para>For example, consider the entry:</para>

<screen>book toc,figure</screen>

<para>This indicates that whenever a <sgmltag>book</sgmltag> is formatted, a
Table Of Contents and a List of Figures should be generated. Similarly,</para>

<screen>/chapter toc</screen>

<para>indicates that whenever a document <emphasis>that has a root
of</emphasis> <sgmltag>chapter</sgmltag> is formatted, a Table of
Contents should be generated. The entry <literal>chapter</literal> would match
all chapters, but <literal>/chapter</literal> matches only <sgmltag>chapter</sgmltag>
document elements.</para>

<para>Generally, the longest match wins. So, for example, if you want to distinguish
articles in books from articles in parts, you could use these two entries:</para>

<screen>book/article toc,figure
part/article toc</screen>

<para>Note that an article in a part can never match a <literal>book/article</literal>,
so if you want nothing to be generated for articles in parts, you can simply leave
that rule out.</para>

<para>If you want to leave the rule in, to make it explicit that you're turning
something off, use the value <quote>nop</quote>. For example, the following
entry disables ToCs and LoTs for articles:</para>

<screen>article nop</screen>

<para>Do not simply leave the word <quote>article</quote> in the file
without a matching value. That'd be just begging the silly little
path/value parser to get confused.</para>

</refsect1>
</refentry>
