<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!--
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC '-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN'
                      'http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.0/docbookx.dtd'>
-->
<chapter lang="en">
<chapterinfo>
<author>
<firstname>Jirka</firstname>
<surname>Kosek</surname>
</author>
<copyright>
<year>2001</year>
<holder>Ji&rcaron;&iacute; Kosek</holder>
</copyright>
<releaseinfo>$Id: htmlhelp.xml,v 1.1 2002/06/13 20:31:59 chorns Exp $</releaseinfo>
</chapterinfo>
<title>Using the XSL stylesheets to generate HTML Help</title>
<?dbhtml filename="htmlhelp.html"?>

<para>HTML Help (HH) is a help format used in newer versions of Microsoft
Windows and applications written for that platform. The HTML Help format allows
you to pack several HTML files together with images, a table of contents, and
an index into a single file. Windows contains a browser for this file format
and full-text search is also supported on HH files. If you want to know
more about HH and its capabilities, visit the Microsoft <ulink
url="http://msdn.microsoft.com/library/tools/htmlhelp/chm/HH1Start.htm">HTML
Help Start Page</ulink>.</para>

<section>
<title>How to generate your first HTML Help file from DocBook sources</title>

<para>Working with the HH stylesheets is the same as with other XSL DocBook
stylesheets. Simply run your favorite XSLT processor on your document
with the HH stylesheet:</para>

<screen format="linespecific">saxon <replaceable>yourfile</replaceable> <replaceable>/path/to/stylesheets/</replaceable>htmlhelp/htmlhelp.xsl</screen>

<para>The stylesheet imports the standard chunking stylesheet, so a set of
HTML files is created in the usual way. Other files are also created
&ndash; <filename>htmlhelp.hhp</filename> is the project file for the HTML
Help Compiler and <filename>toc.hhc</filename> holds the structure of your
document.</para>

<para>The language identifier for the overall HH file is taken from the top-most
element with a <sgmltag class="attribute">lang</sgmltag> attribute in
your DocBook source. This is perfectly legal for documents in only one
language. If a language is not specified in the document, US English is
used. There is one problem &ndash; MS language codes are country-sensitive,
and this information is not available in the DocBook source. If
the stylesheet selects a bad code for you, edit
<filename>langcodes.xml</filename>, and remove all entries which have
your language code, but are located in an inappropriate country.</para>

<para>The title for the overall HH file is taken from the first title element in your
document. Full-text searching is automatically on. If your document
contains index terms, they are automatically converted to HH ActiveX
objects, which are recognized by the HTML Help compiler.</para>

<para>The stylesheet creates couple other files which are then used as an
input for the HTML Help Compiler (HHC), which is part of <ulink
url="http://msdn.microsoft.com/library/default.asp?url=/library/en-us/htmlhelp/html/hwMicrosoftHTMLHelpDownloads.asp"
>HTML Help Workshop</ulink>. If you have HHC in your path, you can
start conversion to the HH format by running this command:</para>

<screen format="linespecific">hhc htmlhelp.hhp</screen>

<para>If you cannot stand to work without using your mouse, there is alternative
way. Just double-click on the <filename
moreinfo="none">htmlhelp.hhp</filename> file. HH Workshop will be
launched automatically. Generation of the HH file can be started by selecting
<menuchoice moreinfo="none">
<guimenu moreinfo="none">File</guimenu> <guimenuitem
moreinfo="none">Compile</guimenuitem> </menuchoice> from the application's
menu.</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>Customizing generated files</title>

<section>
<title>Enabling navigation links</title>

<para>By default, the HTML Help stylesheet disables navigation links at
the start and the bottom of each page. If you want to enable the
links instead, start your XSLT processor with the parameter <parameter
moreinfo="none">suppress.navigation</parameter> set to 0.</para>

<screen format="linespecific">saxon <replaceable>yourfile</replaceable> <replaceable>/path/to/stylesheets/</replaceable>htmlhelp/htmlhelp.xsl "suppress.navigation=0"</screen>

<para>Another approach is to create a driver file, which overrides
the default parameter value.</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[<xsl:stylesheet xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform"
	        version="1.0">

  <xsl:import href="]]><replaceable>/path/to/stylesheets/</replaceable>htmlhelp/htmlhelp.xsl<![CDATA["/>

  <xsl:param name="suppress.navigation" select="0"/>

</xsl:stylesheet>
]]></programlisting>

</section>

<section>
<title>Generating HTML Help for non-Western European languages</title>

<para>If you are generating HTML Help for non-Western Europe
languages, you should change the output encoding of your files, because
the HTML Help compiler improperly handles UTF-8 and even character
entities in the TOC file and index entries. This can be easily done using a 
<quote>driver</quote> file like this:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[<xsl:stylesheet xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform"
	        version="1.0">

  <xsl:import href="]]><replaceable>/path/to/stylesheets/</replaceable>contrib/htmlhelp/htmlhelp.xsl<![CDATA["/>

  <xsl:param name="htmlhelp.encoding" select="'windows-1250'"/>
  <xsl:param name="default.encoding" select="'windows-1250'"/>
  <xsl:param name="saxon.character.representation" select="'native'"/>

</xsl:stylesheet>
]]></programlisting>

<para>Default encoding is ISO-8859-1 (aka ISO Latin 1). If you get
some strange message about characters from your XSLT processor and
your document is in some of Western European languages, try changing
encoding to <literal>windows-1252</literal>. This encoding is similar
to ISO-8859-1 but contains some additional characters like
<quote>typographical quotes</quote> and dashes.</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>More about customizing</title>

<para>More info will come in a near future (I hope and
believe). Meanwhile look into reference for description of <ulink
url="http://docbook.sourceforge.net/release/xsl/snapshot/doc/html/">HTML Help
specific parameters</ulink>.</para>

</section>

</section>

<section>
<title>Feedback</title>

<para>If you have any comments and suggestions about the HTML Help
stylesheet feel free to contact me at following address
<email>jirka@kosek.cz</email>.</para>

</section>

</chapter>